[Music]
in my latest literature review on the
health promoting properties and
therapeutic applications of chia seeds
i ran to a lot of studies like this
strategies for incorporation of chia
into frankfurters as a health promoting
ingredient after all in recent years
we've seen an increasing pursuit of
healthier lifestyles healthier dietary
habits in response to this
there's been a great deal of interest in
compounds originally present in plants
to provide health benefits in real foods
like hot dogs and indeed reformulated
frank footers with chia contain
significantly greater amounts of plant
protein fiber minerals
in fact given this new nutritional
profile such hot dogs could qualify for
labeling with a variety of nutrition and
health claims and what do you know the
chia enriched restructured pork affects
aged rats fed bad diets so let's slap on
a health label
chia's been eaten for thousands of years
so that would suggest it's at least safe
to eat but does it have any special
benefit it's certainly nutritious got
lots of fiber antioxidants black chia
seeds perhaps more than white plant
protein of course
a source of b vitamins source of
minerals so nutritious sure but
just like nearly any whole plant food
but again any special benefits
there's all sorts of claims out there by
people trying to sell you chia seeds but
to definitively establish their actual
beneficial effects we need a little
something called scientific evidence
instead of just cultural tradition
percival leafs or
inaccurate advertising which is a
redundant term if i've ever heard one
for example there are about 50 000
videos on youtube on chia seeds and
belly fat
but what does the science say
dietary chia seeds does reduce belly fat
and rats does apparently reduce the
weight of chickens evidently people
don't like smelling or tasting fishy
chicken so by feeding chickens chia
seeds you can boost their omega-3 levels
without it turning into funky chicken
but what happens if you just cut out the
middle hen
and eat chia yourself
what happens if you add a teaspoon or
two of chia seeds to yogurt as a snack
after the yogurt with the chia
participants reported significantly less
hunger
and that then later translated to eating
fewer calories two hours later at lunch
my initial thought was uh give people
more food add chia to whatever they're
eating and they're less hungry
duh
but no they gave people less yogurt to
compensate so each snack had the same
number of calories so we can say at
least that chi seeds are more satiating
than yogurt
but at lunch two hours later they didn't
just eat a little less food but like 25
fewer calories after the chia
a teaspoon of chia seeds only has like
50 calories
yet they ended up eating nearly 300
calories less at lunch
way more than compensating so if you did
that every day ate some chia seeds as a
snack and one teaspoon seemed to work as
well as too
you'd expect to lose weight over time
you don't know though until you
put it to the test
subjects were randomized to a whole
tablespoon of chia seed twice a day for
months before the first and last meal
for 12 weeks and they found
chia seed does not promote weight loss
after all
huh
well we know from the flaxseed
literature if you give people muffins
made out of whole flax seeds they don't
seem to really absorb all the benefit
compared to ground flaxseed muffins and
the same appeared to be true with chia
seeds
eat
whole chia seeds for 10 weeks and no
increase in short chain omega-3 levels
or long-chain omega-3s but eat the same
amount of chia seeds ground up and
levels shoot up
so maybe the problem with this study is
that they gave people whole chia seeds
there's never been a study on ground
chia and weight loss
until
now
a randomized controlled trial about two
tablespoons of ground chia a day versus
a fiber match control made mostly of oat
bran
that's how you know it wasn't funded by
a chi seed company because they put it
head to head against a real control not
just a sugar pill or something to
control for the fiber content
so then if there was weight loss i mean
we know it wasn't just the fiber but
something particular to the chia and
those eating the ground chia
lost significantly more weight
significantly more waste in terms of
waist circumference a measure of belly
fat and as a bonus c-reactive protein
levels suggesting an anti-inflammatory
effect as well so
maybe some of those 50 000 youtube
videos weren't completely off
there is one form of chia powder i'd
stay away from though i've talked about
using chia gel to replace eggs or oil
and baking you mix a teaspoon of seeds
with a quarter cup of water and let it
sit for half an hour
certainly a way to lower cholesterol but
here you are cutting down on your
salmonella risk and
there was an international outbreak of
salmonella linked to sprouted chia seed
powder
sprouting can create an ideal
environment for bacterial growth
94 people infected across 16 states
granted not as bad as salmonella tainted
eggs which may sicken 79 000 americans
every year but still i would recommend
staying away from sprouted chia seed
powder
[Music]
so
you